in this video I'm going to try to take a
hand at seeing how this thing works in
multimedia which is to say that I'm
going to take a topic that I've recently
addressed in text on the post called
thinking and simulated thinking and
address it here in video and see what
the differences are so this topic has to
do with an effort to consider the
different ways that people go about
making sense of and responding to their
environment and specifically a
distinction between what I'm calling
properly thinking and something else
that seems to be quite prevalent in our
contemporary environment that I'm
calling simulated thinking and the
notion is first and foremost that inside
the concept of thinking there is at
least one major distinction I'm certain
they're more but there's there's at
least one which is between an approach
to the environment that is tuned to an
adaptive to novelty I might think about
this as well in the post I call it
Explorer mode so here we are listening
closely observing closely very little
preconceived notions about what it is
that we're perceiving and in many ways
slowly and carefully in somewhat lightly
grasping things that are in fact not
well understood and endeavoring to come
to grips with them on their own terms so
this is Explorer mode and then standing
in contrast to Explorer mode is what I
called a habit mode so in habit mode we
have some framework for making sense of
responding to our environment at the
example I used was after you have
learned how to drive a car that have it
a driving car so very quickly you can
take your previously
frame that has very crisp patterns that
it can recognize and very specific
responses that it can activate and so in
habit mode our our job is to do a good
job at quickly recognizing predefined
patterns and then effectively executing
scripts for predefined and practiced
responses and so these two modes are
adaptive to different conditions when we
find ourselves in a circumstance of high
novelty then explorer mode is the right
approach and we find ourselves in
circumstances of low novelty then habit
mode is a generally good approach okay
so one of the things that I think I
failed to do in the text was to really
hammer home the fact that the
distinction between explore mode and
habit mode is not the same thing as the
distinction between thinking and
simulated thinking there are different
levels of abstraction
so both explore mode and habit mode are
properly part of thinking thinking
involves the skillful and fluid
application of these different tools in
different environments in some
environments thinking sorry in some
environments explore mode is right and
other environments haven't that is right
and oftentimes women I'd actually did go
back and forth in the same environment
this is all part of thinking simulated
thinking I'm proposin happens when
something breaks down this ability to
fluidly participate in both modes and in
fact maybe even more precisely is when
habit mode there shows up as and
presents itself as thinking and this is
where it gets very dangerous where one
is simulated thinking the individual
actually may believe you possibly quite
earnestly that they are in fact actually
thinking when what they're doing is
actually running some kind of script
some kind of habit
and of course oftentimes some kind of
script there was not necessarily even
theirs in the first place they're
running a third-party script malware as
it were and are largely foreclosed from
Explorer mode right so simulated
thinking is that kind of a thing is not
as simple as merely just habit mode
versus Explorer mode okay so hopefully
that point has some clarity now the the
next thing to think about is why why
does this happen and what does it mean
so one piece to to look at is that
simulated thinking mr. proficiently
outcompetes real thinking in certain
kinds of environments in particular
environments that are static over an
usually long period of time say over a
great moderation particularly when there
is some kind of capacity to engage in
niche construction or the agency of some
organism is able to maintain the stasis
of the environment they're in with their
own activity pushing back on the changes
that are happening in the environment so
what ends up happening is that there's a
feedback loop one's own capacity to
maintain the long duration of some niche
for which a particular set of scripts
were well adapted then makes the use of
scripts a effective strategy and the use
of thinking a ineffective strategy and
as a consequence it becomes not possible
to begin to optimize for using scripts
and to begin to lose the fluid capacity
to then use both explore mode and habit
mode and this begins to move you into
simulated thinking however by itself I
don't think that's enough I think the
next piece is crucial is to
recognized that particularly in this
kind of a static and particularly
artificially static environment um
simulated thinking wins and at edito
basis certainly in the short-term versus
actual thinking simulated thinking is
ability to leverage previously produced
scripts and to deploy them rapidly looks
at first like winning these are the
thinking which is going to be
disoriented and slow and awkward and
oftentimes like saying things that don't
even necessarily make sense or using
terms inappropriately it's it's clumsy
and of course the longer a particular
intelligence has been in a increasingly
artificially static environment the more
this is going to be the case and
effectively if you're have you far
forgotten how to do actual thinking and
everything around you has been teaching
you to engage in simulated thinking
the act of waking up and beginning to
think is you know gonna be a becoming
like a toddler learning how to walk and
so somebody who has been very well
trained as a ballet dancer in spite of
the fact that they may not have done a
single moment of innovation or creation
in that particular formula nonetheless
looks unspeakably elegant compared to
somebody who is beginning the process of
endeavouring to learn how to move their
body under their own agency for the very
first time we say this actually quite
easily in the performance art known as
debate you know a debate we normally do
is very much in the in the direction of
a habit mode and as a consequence can
quite often fall into simulated thinking
and what a debater is engaging in a
pattern recognition and rapid response
activity with
perhaps a specific small amount of
focused thinking controlling the
structure it's a bit like a like a
military commander who's exercising
over a very can achill old-fashioned
like Frederick the great kind of
military commander a very mechanical
army but nonetheless as a leadership
possession and it still needs to be
engaging in some level of thinking so
you know in debate he developed skillful
perception of rhetorical strategies and
develop a portfolio of effective
responses and then our job is largely to
simply deploy this repertoire and it's
habit where you practice it you practice
a little vigorously and under intense
conditions so that you are like a good
boxer capable of deploying it
effectively and there's utility to this
but I think we should be clear that the
primary utility is investing someone in
a social conversation and that is at all
conducive to collaborative thinking so
that what ends up happening is that when
someone shows up who's actually trying
to engage in collaborative thinking and
someone else deploys the toolkit of
debate the debater will show up as
winning at least to those who aren't
watching closely and the thinker will
show up as being oftentimes really
rather stupid and so you mean nobody
wants to emulate that and so what is up
happening is that it begins to select
against thinking in both directions
which is to say people who are trying to
think lose and other people don't even
try because it just looks like a bad
choice and this shows up all over the
place you know the political infighting
is of this sort think about yourself
like in an academic department where you
have a distinction between a an earnest
and perhaps somewhat unsophisticated
graduate student who's really struggling
with something difficult and a practiced
courtier
Jr professor who's quite skilled in the
fine art of using rhetoric to out-group
somebody socially or politics inside a
corporate bureaucracy it's at a
boardroom for example these are all this
same sort and the point is that there's
a condition under which we first begin
to move into an environment where
simulated thinking becomes more and more
useful and developing skills in just
doing that becomes the way to be
successful in your environment and then
also becomes more more capable of
extinguishing thinking you know removing
it from the field of play and then this
of course is a feedback loop the
structures that are able to do nice
construction become controlled by those
who are engaging in simulated thinking
who then use to the structures to
maintain the integrity of the
environment for which they are well
adapted and as a consequence become even
more well-positioned to extinguish
thinking and to optimize for submitted
thinking and you find yourself stuck
you're not trapped in a particular niche
and this will last until it doesn't
because at the end of the day reality is
at ultimate Lea changing and so even a
very powerful control structures ability
to hold back the waters will all be
overwhelmed by something something
somewhere will ultimately burst the dike
and there will be a flood of novelty
that flows into the niche and
intriguingly enough it generally works
in such a way that the the more that the
niche was constructed the the more that
moderation was imposed by agency the
more novelty will rush in and this is a
little bit like not even but it's a lot
like the relationship between the
complicated and chaos that was talked
about in the episode on the kind of
entrain work so
so this is where we find ourselves now
we're in a circumstance where there has
actually been a great moderation there
has actually been a significant
selection for a long period of time for
simulated thinking and a significant
selection against thinking and at the
same time novelty has been building up
behind the dam massive novelty and so
the dam is now in the process of
breaking and novelty is in the process
of flooding and and of course now what's
happening is the Nisha is shifting we're
thinking and particularly the ability to
enter into collaborative conversation
which is where thinking is at its best
it's once again being established as fit
as adaptive and simulated thinking is
increasingly showing up as as error as
collection in fact it's dangerous there
possibly even bordering on madness in
certain circumstances and that's all I
have to say about that I'm interested to
see for those of you who perhaps have
read the post or for those who haven't
your thoughts on the qualities of doing
this in video versus doing this in text
is one more effective than the other are
they interestingly feeding back on each
other
is it worth my time to do both if you
can help with that one that'd be great